<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Moses message to Pharoah, or God sending to the heads of England go undo the heavy burdens, to let the oppressed go free, to serve Him in the wilderness, that he may do them good in their latter dayes. For Israel shall be many dayes without a king, without a priest, without an ephod, and without a teraphim, afterward they shall look [...]he Lord their God, and David their king, and shall [...]ar the Lord, and his goodness in his latter dayes, ...</title>
            <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 73 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40939</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F491B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R218272</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99829881</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99829881</idno>
            <idno type="VID">34328</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40939)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 34328)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2029:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Moses message to Pharoah, or God sending to the heads of England go undo the heavy burdens, to let the oppressed go free, to serve Him in the wilderness, that he may do them good in their latter dayes. For Israel shall be many dayes without a king, without a priest, without an ephod, and without a teraphim, afterward they shall look [...]he Lord their God, and David their king, and shall [...]ar the Lord, and his goodness in his latter dayes, ...</title>
                  <author>R. F. (Richard Farnworth), d. 1666.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>By Richard Farnworth.</note>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Place and date of publication from Wing.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>Tightly bound and cropped, with loss of print.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Friends House Library, London.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Moses --  (Biblical leader) --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="introduction">
            <pb facs="tcp:34328:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:34328:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Moſes Meſſage</hi> TO PHARAOH,</head>
            <argument>
               <p>OR God ſending to the heads of England, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>o undo the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eavy burdens, to let the oppreſſed go free,<note place="margin">Exod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.9.</note> to ſerve <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im in the wilderneſs, that he may do them good in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>heir latter dayes. For Iſrael ſhall be many dayes <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ithout a King, without a Prieſt, without an Ephod,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 3.4, 5.</note> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nd without a Teraphim, afterward they ſhall look <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>he Lord their God, and <hi>David</hi> their King, and ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ar the Lord, and his goodneſs in his latter dayes, <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>oſ.</hi> 3.4, 5.</p>
               <p>Sent in the time of Iſraels Captivity under <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ah,</hi> and his task-maſters, to call to remembrance <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat the Lord did to proud hard-hearted <hi>Pharaoh</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d his hoſte, then, that did oppreſs and burden <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>em, and would not take warning, till they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>erwhelmed in the red ſea, and he is the ſame God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> power now, that he was then; take warning be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e,<note place="margin">Exod. 14.14, 15, 16, 17, 18, &amp;c.</note> and ſtop not your ears againſt the crys of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>or. Let England be a fred Nation, to ſerve the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ord in his own way, and take off all oppreſſions: for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is grieved at it.</p>
            </argument>
            <p>
               <hi>A word from the Lord, both to-Prieſt and People, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>dges and Juſtices, and curſed Lawyers, which op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſs and burthen the creation, to call to ceaſe from op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſſion, and grinding the faces of the poor,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.17, 18, 19, 20.</note> 
               <hi>and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n to the Lord, by putting away the evil of your doings, relieving the oppreſſed; and with</hi> Zacheus, <hi>to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e to whom you the proud Prieſts, and curſed Lawyers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve taken; in tithes, gifts, bribes, and rewards, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e it to the poor, that they may not want; the Lord
<pb facs="tcp:34328:2"/>doth require it, for that is the ordinance of Chriſt, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> oppreſſion is the ordinance of the divel, and his ſerva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> ye are to whom ye do obey: put off the old man with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> deeds, as pride, and oppreſſion, and grinding the faces the poor; the Lord doth require it, for theſe are or<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of the devil,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. 3.13, 14, 15.</note> 
               <hi>and the Prieſts and Lawyers l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> it wondrous well: The ordinance of Chriſt is to fe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> the hungry, cloth the naked, and let the oppreſſed free; Put this in practiſe,</hi> Iſa. 58.6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Therefore put off lying, it is of the Divel, put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> pride, it is as evil; put off covetouſneſs, it is uncivi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> put off heady-high-mindedneſs and envy, for they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> cruel;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 4.20.</note> 
               <hi>and he that envies is a murderer, and no m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>derer hath eternal life abiding in him,</hi> 1 Joh. 8.15. <hi>A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> he that ſaith he loves God, and keepeth not his co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments, is a lyar, and the truth is not in him,</hi> 1 Jo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 2.4. <hi>And he that abideth not in the Doctrine of Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> he hath not God,</hi> 2 Joh. 1.9. Joh. 8.44. <hi>and Ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> ſaith, Reſiſt not evil, but abſtaine from all appeara<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of it. And the ſervant of the Lord muſt be gentle <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> wards all, even towards them that oppoſe themſelve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and he ſaith, Put on as the elect of God, bowels of c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> paſſion, humbleneſs of mind, meekneſs, long-ſufferi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and forbearing one another; and if any man have quarrel againſt another, forgive him freely,</hi> Coloſ. 3.1 <hi>and if ye forgive men their treſpaſſes, your heavenly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther will forgive you your treſpaſſes; and if ye forgi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> not men their treſpaſſes, neither will your heavenly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ther forgive you your treſpaſſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>How do the Prieſts of</hi> England <hi>walk according theſe Scriptures, that deny them in practiſe? As the Priests in</hi> York-<hi>ſhire do, that impriſon the ſervants the moſt high God, for teſtifying against their deceits, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſome of them have lain in priſon neer hand a yeer, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> never could have his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>yal by the Laws of England; ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> a Turk would allow more freedome. It is high time, the Lord to draw his glittering ſword, and exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> judgement upon the unjuſt. See, do theſe Prieſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:34328:2"/>Lawyers walk any wayes anſwerable to the Scriptures?</hi> Wo to the wicked, It ſhall be ill with them,<note place="margin">Iſa. 3.1</note> 
               <hi>Iſa.</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Take warning betime, leſt the judgements of God come upon you at unawares, ye heads and rulers, prieſts and Lawyers, and deſtroy with a ſore deſtruction. Now you have time, prize it, and turn to the Lord with all your hearts, that he may have mercy upon you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Written from the Spirit of the Lord,<note place="margin">Ezek. 1 18, 19. Dan. 10 Heb. 12.</note> by one whom the people of the world calls A Quaker, By name, <hi>Rich. Farnworth,</hi> Whoſe name is written in the Book of Life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 12.17. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1, 2, 3.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>Oh England return unto the Lord, leſt his indignation come upon thee at unawares.</head>
            <p>O Iſrael return to the Lord, for thou haſt faln by thine iniquity,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 14.</note> and art at a diſtance from thy Maker, remember from whence thou art faln, and return, now the Lord is calling upon all people, in all places to return from the evil of their doings, that he may have mercy upon them,<note place="margin">Rev. 2.5 14, 15, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> all people whoſe minds are yet in the earth, and are delighting in vanities, you are faln from your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker,<note place="margin">Iſa. 55.6, Iſa. 19.</note> and are hewing to your ſelves broken ciſterns, that will hold no water, forming up wayes of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips, according to your imaginations, and ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhips the work of your own hands,<note place="margin">Iſa. 29.1</note> delighting in
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:34328:3"/>them,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2.22.</note> O <hi>ceaſe from man, whoſe breath is in his noſtrils, for wherein is he to be accounted of?</hi> All mans teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing is vain, and it doth exalt and feed the fleſhly man,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l. 5.19, 21.</note> and keeps that alive which muſt be deſtroyed, and it leads to vanity it ſelf, the fruit of it is made manifeſt; Iſrael after the fleſh, are not the people of the onely true God,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>l. 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 26.7, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> it is Iſrael after the ſpirit of that the Lord delights in, he makes his abode with the ſons of men, he is purifying their hearts, that he may have an holy people, to place his name in, the Lord is now leading Iſrael to his choſen ones,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 66.1, 2,</note> through the ſea of troubles, and perſecutions, to bring them into the wilderneſs out of all the earthly delights,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or. 6.16 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>v. 2.8, 9, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, 11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 28.9.</note> and earthly vanities, to win them from all the worlds wayes, and worſhips, and cuſtomes, and faſhions, and delights, and outſide teachings of men, that he alone may be their teacher himſelf, as he led Iſrael after the fleſh out of Egypt, from under proud hard-hearted <hi>Pharaoh,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 31.34. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 54.13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>b. 8.10,</note> which was an oppreſſor, and kept them in bondage, that they could not ſerve him, till he had them out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> through the ſea into the wilderneſs, where the Egyptians could not come,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 2.27. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h. 14.26. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o. 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, &amp;c.</note> but as they purſued hard after them, they was deſtroyed, and could not come o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the ſea to them, where the Lord had carryed them, there to make to make his love manifeſt to them; there the Lord did teach them, and gave them a law to walk by, and made a Covenant with them, which covenant they broke, and forgot the mercies of the Lord, which he had made manifeſt to them in a large meaſure,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>o. 15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 47. &amp;c. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 48.1, 2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 59. cap. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>. 1.21, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, 23, 24.</note> and a carnal part go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> up in them after they had back ſlided and faln from their maker, and then oppreſſion got up amongſt them, and pride, and they then ground the faces o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the poor, and lived in luſt and exceſs, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got to execute true Judgement and Juſtice among the people, and the Lord ſaw it, and it did greatly
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:34328:3"/>diſpleaſe him; and he ſent his true Prophets to cry out againſt them;<note place="margin">Hoſ. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> &amp; 9 1, 2. Hoſ. 14.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Iſa. 3.11 12, 13, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 15, &amp;c. Iſa. 3.17 &amp;c.</note> and to tell them that they had faln from their maker, O Iſrael return, return ſaith the Lord, why do ye grinde the faces of the poor? becauſe the daughters of <hi>Sion</hi> are haughty, and walk with ſtretched out necks, and wanton eyes, walking and mincing as they go, and making a tinkling with their feet, therefore the Lord will ſmite with a ſcab, from the crown of the head to the ſole of the foot, and will diſcover all their ſecret parts. The Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the Lord was to come upon them, except they did <hi>return from the evil of their doings;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 28.1,</note> for ſo long as they were kept in the fear of the Lord, it cauſed them to walke humbly before the Lord,<note place="margin">Deut. 10 12, 13, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 15, &amp;c. Heb. 8.13</note> and they <hi>kept his ſtatutes, and his ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, which he had committed to them;</hi> he gave them a law to walk by, and made a covenant with them, in which covenant they had many prieſts; and theſe prieſts was to offer up ſacrifice, and they was to do it without money,<note place="margin">Heb. 7.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 27, 28.</note> and the people they was to bring <hi>of the beſt, the pure and the clean,</hi> and they was to bring it in freely to be offered up in ſac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rifice: in bringing the beſt, they brought their hearts with them; the preiſts offering it up without money, was a figure of Jeſus Chriſt, being the Saints high prieſt, to offer up their ſacrifice to the father freely:<note place="margin">Numb. 28. &amp; 29. ch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Heb. 7.23 &amp;v. 24, &amp;<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> Heb. 9.8, 9, 10, 11, 12 &amp;c. Heb. 9.13<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Heb. 9.18 19, 20. Heb. 9.14 15.</note> and the people bringing it in freely, and of the beſt, the pure, and the clean, was a figure of Jeſus Chriſt, laying down his life freely: and as the life of the creature was to be ſacrificed up, for <hi>the purifying of the fleſh,</hi> the blood of the covenant, <hi>which could not make him that offered it up clean, as touching the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence,</hi> was a figure of Jeſus Chriſt being to be ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed up, and his blood to be ſhed for the <hi>purifying of the conſcience:</hi> Jeſus Chriſt <hi>who through the eternal Spirit offered up himſelf without ſpot to God the Father,</hi> was for the purification of the inward parts, and in
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:34328:4"/>the firſt covenant which was outward to the Je<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>outwardly;<note place="margin">Chron. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.22, &amp;c. Chron. 1. Acts 47, 48. Cor. 6.19. Cor. 6.16, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. Exod. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.16. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xo. 18.19, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0, 21, 22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ev. 19.15. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> verl. 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eut. 1.16, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7, 18. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eut. 16.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8, 19, 20. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xod. 23.8 Chro. 19.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 6, 7, 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. 33.22. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eb. 12.23 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>am. 5.9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eut. 14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7, 28, 29. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en. 17.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0, 11. Deut. 10.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6, 17. Col. 2.11. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. 56.2. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. 58.13, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. Numb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.32. Heb. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 9.10. mat. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>2.8. Mark. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.27, 28.</note> when they was come into the Inhab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted places, they was to build a temple, which tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple was a figure of Jeſus Chriſt, and the Saint (being the true temple) of the living God; and the firſt covenant, they had Judges outwardly, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they was to be ſuch men as <hi>feared God, and hated <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vetouſneſs;</hi> and they was to Judge the people at <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſeaſons, and they was not to be partial in Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but to hear the cauſe of the poor, as well <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the great, and they was to plead the cauſe of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> poor and the needy, and to Judge righteouſly b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt a man and his neighbour, and they was to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it freely, and not to take neither gifts nor reward for gifts and rewards blinded the eyes of the wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and that was a figure of the Lord being the Judg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Jew inwardly himſelf: and in the firſt con<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they was to pay tythes, and they was to fee the poor, the widdows, the fatherleſs, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtrangers with them, and to ſatisfie ſuch as was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> want, that there might be <hi>no begger in Iſra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> that the Lord might be praiſed, and glorified <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them: in this firſt covenant, which was outward they was to be circumciſed, which was a figu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of the Circumciſion which was to be <hi>with<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> hands;</hi> and in the firſt covenant, they had a Sa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bath outwardly, <hi>Exod.</hi> 31.13, 14. A figure of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> true Sabbath, which the Saints ſhould enjoy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly: and in this Sabbath they was <hi>not to ſp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> their own words, nor think their own thoughts, neith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to carry any burden,</hi> not ſo much as <hi>gather ſticks;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that gathered ſticks on the Sabbath day, was ſton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> to death. Now ſo long as they did abide in covenan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and walked in obedience to the Lord, the Lord bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them, and made his love known unto them; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> when they did tranſgreſs, and broke the covenan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Lord ſent his ſervants the prophets, to crye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:34328:4"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gainſt them, and tell them of their tranſgreſſions: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ee <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1. Chap. <hi>The viſion of</hi> Iſaiah <hi>the ſon of</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>mos, <hi>which he ſaw concerning</hi> Judah <hi>and</hi> Jeruſalem,<note place="margin">Iſa. 1. cha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the dayes of</hi> Uzziah, Jotham, Ahaz, <hi>and</hi> Hezeki<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, <hi>kings</hi> of Judah. The Lord had opened their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>itions to his ſervant the prophet, and ſent him to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he heads of them, to declare unto them their tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>reſſions; ſee verſ. 2. <hi>Hear O heavens:</hi> He called <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>pon the heads of them firſt,<note place="margin">Iſa. 1.2, 3 4.</note> then he called to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eet, All ſorts of people; give ear, <hi>O earth:</hi> this was the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eople that the Lord had made choice of, and gave <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem Statutes and Ordinances to obſerve, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alk by, but when they waxed full and rich, their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earts ran after their riches, they made their riches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir gods, and forgot the Lord their Maker, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id not abide in his covenant, but rebelled againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>him; <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord, I have nouriſhed and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>rought up children, and they have rebelled againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e.</hi> This was the people that the Lord had mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſted his love unto, in ſuch a large manner, as he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>id, in bringing them out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> where they had been kept in ſuch bondage under <hi>Pharoah:</hi> and by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>is mighty power and out-ſtretched arme, he brought them forth, and ſlew all their firſt born in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and brought his people to the ſea-ſide, and there he renewed his love to them againe, and made his power known in ſuffering the <hi>Egyptians, Pharaoh,</hi> and his hoſt to purſue them thither, and there he kept them ſafe: when they had neither wall nor bulwark to defend them,<note place="margin">Exod. 14<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 18, 19, 20<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 21, 22, 23<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 24, 25, &amp;c.</note> but the Lords own preſence; and when they ſaw no way of deliver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ance, then did the Lords love and mercy, power, and goodneſs, appear wonderfully in making way <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or them to eſcape from their hands; he led them through the ſea, where he kept them ſafe; and the <hi>Egyptians</hi> aſſaying to follow them, was all drowned. Here the Lords love and power was much manifeſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them in their deliverance out of the hands of
<pb facs="tcp:34328:5"/>their enemies; and that which was ſalvation <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them, was deſtruction to the enemies. Now wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they had taſted ſo largely of the love of the Lor<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they yet afterwards revolted, and looked back, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> brought them into the wilderneſs, there to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them; and he gave them Statutes and ordinan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> to walk by, and made a covenant with them, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they did abide in it, and obſerve what he co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them, they ſhould have the full enjoym<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of his love; in this covenant their prieſts was to o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> up the ſacrifice without money, the people was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> bring it in freely of the beſt, the pure and the clea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and their Judges was to judge the people freely, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was to be done freely, and there was not to be a be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger among them, now ſo long as they ſtood in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the Lord, he bleſſed them, and did largely ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> his love known unto them; whilſt they was in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wilderneſs, for fourty yeers together, and the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> kept them there, to humble them, and <hi>prove th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and try what was in their hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 8. ch.</note> 
               <hi>whether they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> keep his commandments or no,</hi> and there he humb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them, and ſuffered them to hunger, and fed th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> with <hi>Manna,</hi> which they knew not, neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their fathers know, that he might make them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> know him, and depend upon him alone, and to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them know that <hi>man doth not live by bread alone,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>by every word that proceedeth out of the mouth of G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> their raiment waxed not old, for fourty yeers tog<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, when they was in the wilderneſs, neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their feet ſwell; there was his love much manife<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to them, that they might know the love of th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord to them, and there the Lord did forewa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> them to be mindful of his covenant with them, to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> obedient to him, when they came into the land th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he did promiſe to them, leſt when they came i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it, where there was fulneſs of all things, that the they ſhould forget him, and turn aſide. Read <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:34328:5"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e eighth Chapter of <hi>Deuteronomy</hi> through, and ſee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Lords own counſel to them, before they came <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>to the promiſed land, a good land, a land of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rooks, and of Water, of Fountaines, and Depths, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat ſpring out of Vallies, and Hills, a land of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heat, a land of Wine, of Barley, and Figgs,<note place="margin">Deut. 8. v<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 11, 12, 13, 14, v. 15.</note> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>omegranates, a land of Oyle-Olive, and Honey, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>land where they was to eat bread without ſcarce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſs, where there was no lack of any thing: Now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e the counſel of the Lord to them, after he had <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>omiſed to bring them into ſuch a good land, out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the wilderneſs, where was a terrible place of firy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erpents, and Scorpions, and drought, where there <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as no water, ſaith the Lord, <hi>Beware that thou for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>et not the Lord thy God, when thou art come into that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ood land, in not keeping his commandments &amp; his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and his ſtatutes, which he had commanded them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſt,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>when thou art full, and haſt built goodly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouſes, and dwell therein, and when thy Herds and Flock <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>re multiplyed, and thy ſilver and gold is multiplyed,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Verſ. 14.</note> 
               <hi>and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll that thou haſt is multiplied, and then thy heart be lifted <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>p, and thou forget the Lord thy God, which hath done ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>reat things for thee.</hi> See Deut. 8. ch. from v. 15. to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd, what great things the Lord did for them; yet notwithſtanding, when they came in to the promiſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and, where there was ſuch fulneſs, they forgot the Lord, that had done ſo great things for them.</p>
            <p>And ſee if this be not the condition of <hi>England,</hi> now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t this preſent: but when they backſlided from the Lord, he ſent his ſervants the prophets to cry out againſt them, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.2. verſ. <hi>Hear, O heavens,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.2.</note> 
               <hi>and give ear, O earth,</hi> ſaith the Lord by his ſervant the prophet, <hi>I have nouriſhed and brought up a people, and they have rebelled againſt me.</hi> The Oxe and the Aſs doth condemne them;<note place="margin">Verſ. 3.</note> he brings the brute beaſts as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ritneſſes againſt them: ſaith he in the 3. verſe, <hi>The Oxe knows his owner, and the Aſs his maſters Crib, but
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:34328:6"/>Iſrael doth not know, my people doth not conſider <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> have nouriſhed and brought up children,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.4, 5, 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. 2.7, 8. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. 3.9, 10, 11, 12, 12, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>and they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> rebelled againſt me: Ah ſinful Nation, a people la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> with iniquity, a ſeed of evil doers, children that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupted, they have forſaken the Lord, they have prov<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the holy One of Iſrael, they are gone away backw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>.</hi> The people was grown proud and haughty: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Chap. 3. pride is got to the height: is it not ſo <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> amongſt thoſe that are the greateſt profeſſors he<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>England,</hi> at this time? and it doth greatly <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> pleaſe the Lord: he hath ſent forth his ſervanu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cry<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> out againſt it, now, as he did then. Iſrael, af<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they had backſlided from the Lord, oppreſſion a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> cruelty got up among them, <hi>their hands was full blood,</hi> and their fingers full of iniquity; as is no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they offered up abundance of ſacrifice, yet ſaith <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Lord, <hi>Who hath required that at your hands? how <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the beautiful City become an harlot?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 1.21, 22.</note> it was ſo then, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it not ſo now? that which makes a profeſſion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> truth, and doth not practiſe it, is ſo now: back<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and gone out of the way, pride is out of the wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> yet proud men makes a profeſſion of love to Go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Chriſt,<note place="margin">Prov. 6.16, 17, 18, 19.</note> but it is now found to be hypocri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and wo, and miſery is their portion: wo to the pro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> and haughty ones,<note place="margin">Iſa. 28.1. Iſa. 59. ch. Jer. 5.28. Iſa. 1.23. Mica. 3.11. Iſa. 1.21, 22, 23. Iſa. 59.7, 8, 9. &amp; v. 13, 14, 15. Zeph. 3.1, 2, 3, 4. Mal. 3.15.</note> pride is an abomination to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Lord, and the divel he is the king of pride; <hi>E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> now ſwells with pride, and haughtineſs, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> cruelty, and oppreſſion, and grinding the faces <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the poor, and no juſtice nor judgement is exe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in the land, the Lord is ſore diſpleaſed at it; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> it was with Iſrael after the fleſh, ſo is it with Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land now, ſaith the Lord to them by the prophe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. <hi>How is the beautiful City become an harlot! it was f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of judgement; righteouſneſs did lodge in it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> now murderers;</hi> It was ſo then, but is it not ſo now where the Lord hath diſcovered, and laid op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the deceits of the people, to any of his ferva<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:34328:6"/>now, as he did to <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> and ſent them to cry out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gainſt them, they have ſome of them beaten, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>me of them ſtoned, and ſome of them impriſoned, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a Popiſh law, and doth not give them ſo much <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave, as theeves and robbers, but ſhuts them up <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>oſe by a popiſh law, and profeſſeth themſelves to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſtians;<note place="margin">Acts 3.18, 19. Acts 4.1, 2, 3, verſ. 6. to the 22. Act. 5.11, 16, 17. ver. 25. to the 34. Act. 7.51, &amp;c. Act. 17.5, &amp;c. Act. 18.12, &amp;c. Mat. 5.39, 40, 41, 42, 43, 44, 45, 46, 47, 48<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Rom. 12.10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, 20, 21<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Hoſ. 6.9. Joh. 3.15. Mat. 23.10 to the end of the Chap. Luk. 11.46 to verſ. 53</note> but now they are made manifeſt to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of that generation that perſecuted the ſervants <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f the Lord, and are of the generation of <hi>Cain,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd are no Chriſtians, but enemies to Jeſus Chriſt: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>either Chriſt, nor the Saints of God ever perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ted or impriſoned any, but was perſecuted and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>priſoned, and by thoſe that made the greateſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rofeſſion of love to God, but was the greateſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nemies to the truth of God, as it is now, <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.40. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ain</hi> was a perſecuter from the beginning, and where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>erſecution is now, it is from <hi>Cains</hi> generation, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eſus Chriſt ſaid to his, <hi>Love your enemies, bleſs them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>hat curſe you, do good to them that hate you, and pray <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>or them that deſpitefully uſe you, that ye may be chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ren of your heavenly Father, for if ye love them that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ove you, what reward have you, do not Publicanes ſo? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ut I ſay unto you, Love your enemies, and if thine enemy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>unger, feed him; If he thirſt, give him drink; and who o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ver ſhall ſmite thee on the one cheek, turn to him the other alſo. Reſiſt not evil, but abſtaine from all ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance of it,</hi> and <hi>do unto all men as ye would they ſhould do unto you.</hi> Now he that abideth not in the doctrine of Chriſt, is a Divel: Chriſt never perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted; he that profeſſeth love to Chriſt, and acts contrary to him, is Antichriſt; and ſo is an enemy to Chriſt, devourers and murderets; the truth is impriſoned by the laws, and may not be ſuffered to ſpeak, and all manner of evil is freed, and at li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty: pride is at liberty, covetouſneſs at liberty, envy at liberty, lying, and ſwearing, and drunken<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs at liberty; <hi>becauſe of oaths the land mourns;</hi> Chriſt Jeſus is impriſoned, and <hi>Barabbas</hi> ſet free, as
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:34328:7"/>it was,<note place="margin">Hoſ. 4.2, 3. Iſa. 1.23. Jer. 5.28, 29. Jer. 7.3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. Jer. 5.30, 31. Mica. 3.11. Jer. 23.16, 17, 18, 19, 20. 2 Chron. 19.4, 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. Iſa. 56.10, 11.</note> it is; <hi>thy princes are rebellious, and compa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> of theeves,</hi> ſaith the Lord by his prophet, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> children of Iſrael: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 1.23. <hi>Every one loveth and followeth after rewards, they judge not the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>leſs, neither doth the cauſe of the poor come unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Is it not ſo now? the ſame deceits that was the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> now; the prieſts they preach for hire, which is a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bomination to the Lord, the falſe prophets did, the true prophets never did, but was ſent to out againſt them. After that the children of Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> had revolted, and backſlided, then they broke covenant of the Lord that he had made with th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the prieſts was to do what they did without mon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> but when they did not, the Lord was diſpleaſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them, and the Lord ſent to cry out againſt the See <hi>Iſa.</hi> 56.10, 11. <hi>His watchmen ore all blind, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and rewards had blinded their eyes, and they l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> every one for his gaine from his quarter,</hi> The <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> teachers did ſo then, do they not ſo now? e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> one looks for his gaine from his quarter, and wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they are. <hi>Iſaiah</hi> was a true prophet of the Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> as he had received freely of the Lord, he ſpoke f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to them again: and ſaid, <hi>Ho every one that thirſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ome and receive freely, without money or price: Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> was a true prophet of the Lord,<note place="margin">Iſa. 55.1, 2.</note> and was ſent to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> out againſt the falſe prophets; and he did not l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> for any gaine,<note place="margin">Joh. 1. Iſa. 29.23, 24. Joh. 6.8. 1 Cor. 1.27, 28, 29. 2 Cor. 6.7, 8, 9, 10. Rev. 3.9, 10, 11, 12, 13.</note> but as he had received freely, ſpoke freely again: <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.1, 2, 3. Where the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> light of God is made manifeſt now, It ſees the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> deceits amongſt the falſe teachers in <hi>England,</hi> he did among the falſe teachers in Iſrael, and ſent by the Lord to cry againſt them; but the di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> is more ſubtil now, then he was then; he is un<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> finer habit of profeſſion, and he hath a guard defend him, he hath got great ſtrength, by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ting off the Popes head, and ſets it to defend <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by, that if any come to ſpeak againſt his deceit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:34328:7"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ath the Popes law to lay hold on him by,<note place="margin">1 <hi>Mary</hi> 2. <hi>Aſſerti on</hi> 3. <hi>Chap. But ſee firſt of Eliz.</hi> 2. <hi>Cha. laſt clauſe. Sir Niche<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Hides cited that it was repeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, Dolt.</hi> 103.104. <hi>p.</hi> Rev. 17.7, 8, 9, 80, 11, &amp;c. Rev. 22.11, 12. Rev. 19. ch. Rev. 21. to the 8. &amp; v. 22. to the end. Joh. 10.1. Jer. 23.30, 31. Hoſ. 6.9. 1 Joh. 3.15. 1 Cor. 6.9, 10, 11. Iſa. 1.28. Iſa. 48.16. Jer. 5.30, 31. Rev. 18.1, 2, &amp;c.</note> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a priſon to put him into, and ſo he is ſafe; the beaſt ſits acting there, as in a ſtage-play for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ey, and if any be ſent by the Lord to ſpeak a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt him, when he hath done, though the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t profeſſed ſo much love to Chriſt, that he might <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> a little time, to ſpeak after the beaſt had done, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he ſtage-players are ſo cunning, and had train<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>p their ſchollers ſo much, that there is a combi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on among them all, to uphold the kingdome <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ntichriſt ſtill, that ſpeak when he hath ended play; and he calls upon his followers to take away, and ſaith he makes an uproare, and ſo he very way armed againſt the Lord, and hath the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ices to take his part, and will not ſuffer the truth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e declared: But the Lord is coming in power, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>verturn all powers, but his own, and he alone <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> rule and raign for ever, and ever, and nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt ſtand but his own pure being, <hi>Zeph.</hi> 3.8, 9. All <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eits, and deceivers, and theeves, and robbers, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſt be caſt out, into the lake that burneth, he will <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> have a deceitful perſon to dwell in his houſe, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>y with all deceivers, the Lord is coming to judge, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> avenge himſelf upon all. <hi>Jeremiah</hi> he was a true <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>phet of the Lord, and he was ſent to cry out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>nſt the falſe ones: See <hi>Jer.</hi> 5. <hi>A horrible and a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y thing is committed in the land; the prophets pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>y falſely, and the prieſts bear rule by their means, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the people love to have it ſo:</hi> It was ſo then, but is not ſo now? and the Lord ſent to cry againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>m, and ſo doth he now. Down with them, down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h them; the day of vengeance is coming upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h them, and all that holds them up, except we <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> repent, and turn to the Lord ſpeedily, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>7.</p>
            <p>Oh England, England, repent, and turn to the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rd, ſit down in duſt and aſhes, the day of the
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:34328:8"/>Lord is coming upon thee, to judge thee, and his power known upon the heads of it, except ſpeedily return, and meet the Lord, by yielding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dience to him. Down with all oppreſſion; the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of the poor of England, is entred into the ears <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Lord of Sabbaths, the ſins of England do teſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gainſt their face, iniquity is at height, ready <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cut down to the ground. England, England day of the Lord is come upon thee; hear yet <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Heads and Rulers, the Lord hath a contro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> with you; he looketh for judgement and j<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> but behold cruelty and oppreſſion; he will re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> all the righteous blood that is ſpilt at your ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> you kill and ſlay the righteous ones of the Lord is ſent to teſtifie againſt your deceits; now you all be left without excuſe, he hath ſent bo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> high and low, to forewarme them, and this is to<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> O heads, it is required at your hands to have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Juſtice, and to have heard the cauſe of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and to have ſeen that true Juſtice and Judge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had been executed; but behold nothing but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty and oppreſſion: you have impriſoned the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſuffered it to be trodden under foot, and witneſſes lies ſlaine in the ſtreets by you: <hi>Ah, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the Lord, <hi>I will eaſe me of mine enemies, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> me of my adverſaries.</hi> Ye ſay as the children <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rael did, after they had backſlided, and broke<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> covenant of the Lord, as they did to whom the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet <hi>Micah</hi> was ſent to cry againſt, <hi>Prophecy ye</hi> ſay they to them that prophecy; ſo ſay you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſhuts up and impriſons ſome, and beateth ſtoneth others, and ſuffers it to be ſo by your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and will not let the truth declare it ſelf unto y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> but ſaith the Lord, <hi>Ariſe and depart, for this i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> your reſt, becauſe it is polluted, it ſhall deſtroy y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ven with a ſore destruction,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mica. 2.10, 11, 12, 13.</note> Mich. 2.10, 11, 12, Hear this, Oh heads of England, Is it not for
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:34328:8"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> know Judgement, who hate the good,<note place="margin">Mic. 3.1, 2, 3, 4.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Iſa. 28.1. Mic. 2.1, 2, &amp;c. Iſa. 38. Iſa. 59.8. Hoſ. 9.7. Mic. 3.9, 10 Hoſ. 13.6, 7, 8. Mic. 3.11. 1 Theſ. 5.2, 3. 2 Theſ. 1.7, 8, 9, 10.</note> and love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e evil? Now you are full, pride ſwelleth amongſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>u, which is odious in the eyes of the Lord: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ur ſins teſtifie againſt you, covetouſneſs abounds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ongſt you, cruelty and oppreſſion ſwells, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd mourns becauſe of oppreſſion, the Lord look<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> down from heaven upon it, and he is ſore diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eaſed at you all, even all the heads of <hi>England,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at abhor judgement, and pervert equity, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ild up Sion with blood, ſlayes the righteous ones, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> your laws, the <hi>heads thereof judge for rewards,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d <hi>the prieſts thereof teach for hire, and lean upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Lord, and ſay, Is not the Lord amongſt us? and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> cannot come upon us: but when ye cry peace, peace, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>n cometh ſudden deſtruction from the Almighty,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>yeth all the unjuſt.</p>
            <p>Many great deliverances hath the Lord given to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>is nation, never like to any but Iſrael; and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r all theſe large deliverances, his mercy is forgot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d his grace is turned into wantonneſs; and haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>eſs, and many large promiſes have been made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e after time, that this nation ſhould be free <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>om tyranny: and never the like was ſeen in any <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>tion, profeſſing Chriſtianity: but here is nothing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> all performed, but a ſecond beaſt is ſet up, worſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>en the firſt, and all the world wonders, and wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ips the beaſt, but thoſe who have found their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mes written in the book of life; and the beaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>akes war with the Saints,<note place="margin">Rev. 17.8, 9, 10, 11, &amp;c. Verſ. 14. Rev. 14.9, 10, 11. Iſa. 29.13, 14. Mat. 16.21<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> but the Saints ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>vercome, and the beaſt, and beaſtly worſhip ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e caſt into the lake that burneth, and they ſhall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve no reſt day nor night, that worſhip the beaſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d his Image, and that receive the mark of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eaſt: all the worſhip of the world is beaſtial, wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iping the work of their own hands, and the prieſts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e the greateſt enemies to Jeſus Chriſt now, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e is appearing in Spirit, as they was, when he came
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:34328:9"/>in the fleſh,<note place="margin">Mat. 21.15, 16. ver. 23. Mat. 20.18, 19. Mat. 26.14, 15. ver. 47.57, 59, &amp;c. Heb. 8.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0, 11, &amp;c. Jer. 31.31, 32, 33, 34.</note> to fulfill what the law did contai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> after that the Lord had made a covenant with I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>el after the fleſh, and they did not abide in it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> broke it, then he promiſed that the would <hi>m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> new covenant with the houſe of Iſrael, and the ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> Judah, but not according to the firſt covenant, wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> covenant they broke, notwithſtanding he was an husb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> to them; but this is the covenant that I will make <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> them, after thoſe dayes, ſaith the Lord, I will put <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> laws in their hearts, and in their minds will I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them, ſaith the Lord, and they ſhall not need to tea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>very man his brother, and every man his neighbour, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, know the Lord; for they ſhall all know me, from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> leaſt to the greateſt,</hi> and ſaith the Lord by the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> ſpeaking of Chriſt, <hi>I will give thee f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> covenant of the people, for a light of the Gentiles, open the blind eyes, to bring the priſoners out of priſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> and them that ſit in darkneſs into the ſhaddow light.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now this was foretold of by the prophets, <hi>Iſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and <hi>Jeremiah,</hi> and the Lord did perform his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, made by the prophets concerning his co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nant: Jeſus Chriſt was foretold to be his new co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nant; and when Jeſus Chriſt which was foretold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> by the prophets came to fulfill and put to an end <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> that was contained in the firſt covenant, all t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Jews, chief Prieſts, Scribes, and Phariſees, Elde<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and Rulers of the people ſought to put him <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> death, becauſe he came to teſtifie againſt the d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceits that they then lived in; for, ſaith Jeſus Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> himſelf, <hi>Becauſe,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>I teſtifie againſt the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> that their deeds are evil, therefore doth the world h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> me,</hi> It is the ſame now as it was then, where Jeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt is made manifeſt in the hearts of his peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Now when Jeſus Chriſt came in that ſingle perſon,<note place="margin">Heb. 8.6, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 8, 9, 10, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eb. 10.9.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> came to put an end to the firſt covenant, which wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> broken, and to eſtabliſh another, he went into th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:34328:9"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mple, and into the Synagogues, witneſſing the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>filling of the Law, and ſaid to the people,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.15, 16. ver. &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Think <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that I am come to deſtroy the law: I am not come to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ſtroy, but to fulfill the law,</hi> and he took the book, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d he read that place of <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> where he had pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſied, and foretold of him, and ſaid, <hi>This day is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>s Scripture fulfilled in your cars:</hi> now, againe he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d that <hi>heaven and earth ſhould paſs away, but not <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> joi, and one title of the word, ſhould in no wiſe fail <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all was fulfilled;</hi> he came for the fulfilling: af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> that Jeſus Chriſt was ſacrificed up,<note place="margin">Heb. 8.1.2 ver. 6, 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12. Heb. 10.1. ver. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9, 10. Iſa. 33.22. v. John 4.20, 21, 22. John 4.23, 24.</note> which was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> everlaſting ſacrifice, then all the Types, Figures, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d ſhaddows, was to be put to an end, all things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at was contained in the firſt covenant, both prieſts, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>thes; ſacrifices, and burnt-offerings, and all things <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at was outward and carnall, the Law outwardly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d the Judges, Lawgiver, and Kings, for he was both <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dge, Lawgiver, and King himſelfe; that temple <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ich was outward, was to be diſannulled after that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was ſacrificed up, and that worſhip, for ſaith he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to the Woman of <hi>Samaria,</hi> in the 4 of <hi>John: Yee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rſhip yee know not what, wee worſhip wee know what: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> the hour cometh and now is, when yee ſhall neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>rſhip at Jeruſalem, nor at this Mount,</hi> which had been <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e chiefeſt places of worſhip, but they ſhould now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>orſhip at neither of them, but they that worſhip <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e Father, ſhould worſhip him nearer hand, even in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>irit and in truth: and after that Jeſus Chriſt was <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>crificed up, which was the everlaſting ſacrifice, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſe was all to be ended; and the Apoſtles who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>re made to partake of the ſubſtance of the ſecond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>venant, which was Chriſt in them, they went <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th into the temple, and into the ſynagogues, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>aw the Jewes off from that outward worſhip, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eached the reſurrection of Jeſus from the dead,<note place="margin">Jonn 3.31, 32, 33, 34, 35, 36, ver.</note> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>riſt was riſen out of all thoſe Ordinances; they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s dead, there was no life in them; Chriſt which
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:34328:10"/>was the life of them, was riſen out of them; the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had been a beauty, and an excellency in them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the time that they was commanded, but now <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſubſtance of them was come, and the glory of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Lord was departed out of them, both out of the ou<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward worſhip, and out of the outward temple, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they was ſent to declare againſt it, and to draw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from it:<note place="margin">Acts. 7.47, 48, 49. ver.</note> 
               <hi>Steven</hi> hee went and witneſſed againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and ſaid, <hi>God that made the world did not dwell <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> temples made with hands, neither was hee to be wo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped there,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 6.10, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1, 12, 13, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>4. ver. Act. 7.57, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8, 59. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 10.27, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8, 29, 30, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>1. ver. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on. 8.59. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er.</note> Acts 7. And they ſaid he came to ove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne the Statutes, and Ordinances given out <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Moſes,</hi> and for witneſſing of the truth was he ſton<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to death, by them of uncircumciſed hearts a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> eares: and it is the ſame generation now, that ſtone<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the ſervants of the Lord; the ſtony hard hearts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> untaken away yet in thoſe, that either ſtoneth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> countenanceth them that doth, they was yet nev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> circumciſed, with the circumciſion made witho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> hands, but are ſtifnecked and enemies to Jeſus Chri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Joh.</hi> 8.41, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> All that the Prieſt had for offering <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſacrifices, in the firſt Covenant, they was to pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> take of the things ſacrificed, and offered up; and the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had rythes becauſe they had no part nor portion <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the promiſed land; &amp; with thoſe tythes the poor, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> widdow, and the ſtrangers, and fatherleſs, were to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> filled and ſatisfied, out of them, <hi>that the Lord G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> might bleſs them.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Deut. 14, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>7, 28, 29. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er.</note> But when the Prieſts took mony <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> what they did, the Lord was diſpleaſed with the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſent his true Prophets to cry out againſt the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> take the tythes from the Prieſt, and take off that op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion that is upheld by the Lawyers; for the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are taskemakers, as the taskemakers in <hi>Egypt,</hi> th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> doe burthen and oppreſs the Creation. Undoe th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> heavy burthens that the people groans under <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> theſe oppreſſors, and let the oppreſſed go<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ree, th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Lord doth require it, and let there not be any want
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:34328:10"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>member the poore that are in wants, that they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay have food and rayment, and be filled and ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>fied: ſeek not your ſelves but the good of others, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at the Lord God may bleſs you; let love run <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>th to all, and let it be without diſſimulation, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Goſpell will be preached to every Creature, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> love is the fulfilling of the law, and Jeſus Chriſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> is the love of the Father, and he is the end of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w for righteouſneſs, to them that believe,<note place="margin">Rom. 8.4.</note> 
               <hi>who walk <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> after the fleſh, but after the ſpirit,</hi> be not profeſſors <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> poſſeſſors; If you know him, he is all love, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>rcy, and bowels of compaſſion, and he laid downe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> life, to take away the tythes and oppreſſion; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>low him in his example, you that profeſs your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es to be Chriſtians, for <hi>he that is in Chriſt is a new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ature,</hi> and he that ſaith he is in Chriſt, <hi>ought to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ke as hee walked,</hi> and <hi>hee went about doing good;</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>refore do good unto all, by undoing the heavy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dens, and letting the oppreſſed go free, <hi>remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> them that are in bonds, as bound with them,</hi> and <hi>do <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> all, as you would be done by,</hi> or elſe never profeſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e love to God and Jeſus Chriſt, for hee will call <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> to account, and workers of iniquity muſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> from his preſence; thoſe that acts in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>teouſneſs, who lives in pleaſure and wanton<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, pride and haughtineſs, idleneſs and ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> of bread, which were the ſins of <hi>Sodom</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the ſins of <hi>England,</hi> forgetting the poore that are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ants, bonds and impriſonments, but the Lord is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing to viſit his people that are impriſoned by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and will returne upon you the evill of your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gs, for in as much as you doe it to them, you doe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> him; and ſee what he ſaith,<note place="margin">Matth. 25.41, 42, 43, 44, 45, 46.</note> in <hi>Matth.</hi> 25.41, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>3, 44, 45, 46. ver. <hi>Paul</hi> who was a true Miniſter <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſus Chriſt, he was impriſoned by the Jews for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eſſing the truth, and <hi>Silas</hi> was impriſoned, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and <hi>John,</hi> and were beaten, and others were
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:34328:11"/>ſtoned for witneſſing the truth, by the Jews th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> were enemies to Jeſus Chriſt; and now the ſa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> things is acted by the men of this generation, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Prieſts and Lawyers are the greateſt ene<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> now, as they was then; but thus ſaith the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Wo unto the wicked, it ſhall be ill with them; but ſay<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> the righteous,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſa. 3.10. v.</note> 
               <hi>It ſhall go well with them.</hi> Now you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> doth profeſs love to God and Chriſt, and foun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> be of that generation that ſlew the righteous bl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> in former ages, and this is the ſame generat<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> which kils and ſlayes the righteous ones in y<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> hearts, and keeps them in bonds and priſons; but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> becauſe the ſeed of God is impriſoned in you: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you that doth ſo, knows not Jeſus Chriſt, who <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Love your enemies,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Luke 11.46, 47, 48, 49, 50, 51, 52.</note> 
               <hi>bleſs them that curſe you, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> for them that hate you and diſpitefully uſe you:</hi> nei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> are you accquainted with the teachings of God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the new Covenant of grace, nor knows not God <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>dwels in a temple made without hanns,</hi> as the Ap<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> did, who was partaker of the new Cove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> which was Chriſt in him,<note place="margin">Gal. 1.15, 16.</note> and his body was made <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> temple of God, and he went and ſpoke againſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> outward temple, and ſaid, <hi>God that made the w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> did not dwell in temples made with hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 17.24, 25.</note> 
               <hi>neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> he worſhipped with mens hands as though he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> any thing, who giveth to all life and breath a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> things; and hath made all Nations of the earth of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> would and one blood, to ſerve him:</hi> and the Apo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> went to draw them off from the outward worſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> to exhort them to mind the light in them tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſhew them ſin and evill, to mind that, and it <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> them into all light;<note place="margin">2 Pet. 1.19. 2 Cor. 4.6. 1 Co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 4.7.10, 11. ver.</note> ſaith he, <hi>Yee have a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> to the which ye do well to take heed unto, as unto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th in a darke place, untill the day dawn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y-Siar ariſe in your hearts;</hi> that light did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>at of all the wayes and works of darkneſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wrought out that carnal part in them, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:34328:11"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hem at a diſtance from the Lord, who received it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd were obedient to it; and it did it did lead them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> purity into righteouſneſs up to the everlaſting <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ay of the Lords love and mercy, and brought all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>at walked in obedience to it, to be united into one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ody, to be of one heart and mind,<note place="margin">Heb. 12.22, 23, 24.</note> to be a family of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve, a houſhould of faith, and they met together, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd waited upon the Lord, and ſpoke their conditi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns one to another, and had no man to ſpeak over <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em,<note place="margin">1 Cor. 14.23.30, 31, 32. Iſa. 54.13, 14.</note> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. chap. God did fulfill his promiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ven forth by <hi>Jeremiah</hi> the Prophet of the Lord, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e new covenant, <hi>Jer.</hi> 31.34. where it is ſaid that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> would teach them himſelf, and in <hi>Iſa.</hi> the 54. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ere it was promiſed by that Prophet, that all the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ildren of the Lord ſhould be taught of the Lord, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>d he would eſtabliſh them in righteouſneſs; All <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o came to enjoy the ſecond covenant, they did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tneſs the ſubſtance of all that made manifeſt in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>em which was ſpoken in the firſt covenant, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s made to the Jew outwardly, <hi>Now he is not a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>w, that is one outwardly, but he is a Jew that is one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>wardly.</hi> The Jew outwardly, he had his cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt outwardly; the Jew inwardly had his cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt inwardly; Chriſt was this covenant, and they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>und him revealed and manifeſted in them: the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w outwardly in the outward covenant, he had a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>w outwardly written in tables of ſtone; the Jew <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>wardly, he had his law inwardly in the new co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nant, written in the fleſhly tables of the heart, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t with Inke, but with the Spirit of the living <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>od: the Jew outwardly, he had his law-giver out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ardly, but the Jew inwardly, he hath his law-gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r inwardly in this ſecond covenant:<note place="margin">Iſa. 33.22. Exod. 18.13. to the 28. Heb. 12.22</note> the Jew out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ardly in the firſt covenant, had his Judges out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ardly, the Jew inwardly he hath his Judge inward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in the ſecond covenant; in the firſt covenant, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>oſes</hi> was to <hi>ſet over the people faithful men, fearing
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:34328:12"/>God, and hating covetouſneſs,</hi> and they was judge the people at all ſeaſons:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>am. 5.9. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>xod. 18.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>0, 21, 22.</note> the Jew inward he hath the Lord to be his law-giver, Iudge, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King, to judge and <hi>condemne ſin in the fleſh, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> right<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ouſneſs of the law may be fulfilled: Chriſt is <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> end of the law</hi> inwardly; <hi>for righteouſneſs,</hi> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne as king for ever: The Jew outwardly in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> firſt covenant, which was outward, had his prop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> outwardly; but the Jew inwardly, he hath his p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet inwardly, even Jeſus Chriſt: the Jew o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly, in the firſt covenant, which was outwa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> had his prieſts outwardly, the Jew inwardly, he h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> his teacher inwardly, in the new covenant, whic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> inward; the Lord alone is the teacher of all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> himſelf alone, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 55. <hi>Ye need not that any man t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> you,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.27.</note> 
               <hi>but as the anointing teacheth you,</hi> 1 Joh. 2.27. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Children of the Lord, are taught of the Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in righteouſneſs are they eſtabliſhed, and are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> from oppreſſion: The Jew outwardly, he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> word outwardly; the Jew inwardly, he hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> word inwardly, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. <hi>The word is nigh thee i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> mouth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 10.8. 1 Cor. 6.19. 2 Cor. 6.16, 17, 18.</note> 
               <hi>and in thy heart;</hi> the Jew outwardly, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his temple outwardly, in the firſt covenant; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Jew inwardly, his temple made without hands, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>bodies made the temples of the living Gad;</hi> the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> outwardly, he had his circumciſion outwardl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the firſt covenant, which was outward, but the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> inwardly, in the ſecond covenant, he hath his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cumciſion inwardly, circumciſed with the circum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on made without hands, the cutting off the bod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſin; the Jew outward, he had his guide outward<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Jew inwardly, his guide inwardly: they that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> guided by the Spirit of God, they are the ſon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God.<note place="margin">Rom. 8.14.</note> The Iew outwardly in the firſt covenant <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> had his ſacrifice outwardly, the life of the crea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> was to be offered up in a ſacrifice, and it did <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> purifie the fleſh, the outward part; <hi>It coul<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:34328:12"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ifie as touching the conſcience, him that offered it up,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Jew inwardly in the new Covenant, the blood Jeſus Chriſt is offered up to purifie the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e: the Jew outwardly, he had his evidence out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rdly, the Jew inwardly, he hath his inwardly; <hi>are is three that bear record in earth, the water,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 5.6, 7, 8<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>9.</note> 
               <hi>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ad, and the ſpirit, and theſe three agree in one.</hi> In the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> covenant, which was outwardly, to the Iew out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rdly, they had a Sabbath outwardly, the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>n of Iſrael after they was come out of Egypt, Lord gave them a Sabbath; a ſabbath is a reſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>gne of the true reſt, which the Saints did injoy in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>iſt, the ſecond covenant, <hi>Heb.</hi> 4. <hi>There is a reſt the people of God;</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 4.9, 10.</note> and he that believeth hath <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> into his reſt,</hi> and <hi>hath ceaſed from his works, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> did from his;</hi> In the firſt covenant, which was ward, their Church was outward, gathered to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>er by an outward command of the letter with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>; in the new covenant, which was inward, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> inwardly, their Church was <hi>in God,</hi> 1 Theſ. 1.1. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> and Silvanus, and Timotheus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Theſ. 1.1. 1 Pet. 2.5, 9.</note> they writ unto <hi>the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uch of the Theſſalonians, which were in God the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>er of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and they was all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ered together, by the light of God in them, that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>t which the Apoſtle did exhort them to be mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of, in 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.19. and that light did lead them, guide them, out of the pollutions of the world, guided them up to purity, to holineſs, to righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>neſs; and they were born againe, begotten, <hi>by the will of man, but by the will of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.18, 19, 20, 21, 22, 23.</note> begot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> by the immortal word, <hi>born of water and the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> and they did walk after the Spirit, in love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>tenderneſs of compaſſion, one towards another, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> was of one heart, and one minde, and was all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>dren of the light, and were guided by the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> God, and their conſciences was purged from <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ncleanneſs, by the blood of the covenat, and
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:34328:13"/>were all gathered together, by the Spirit of tr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> out of all the wayes and works of darkneſs; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> light did lead them out of all the worlds wayes, of all the worlds worſhips, which was outward carnal; ſaith the Apoſtle to them, <hi>Touch not, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not, handle not,</hi> which all are to periſh, with uſing: <hi>Col.</hi> 2.21, 22. This light of God in them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> lead them out of all the worlds cuſtomes and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, which the Apoſtle did exhort them to; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> he, <hi>Be not conformed like unto this world, but be t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> formed by the renewing of your minds, that ye<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> know what is that good, that acceptable, and pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> will of God;</hi> this light of God in them, did them, and guide them out of all the worlds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and did lead them into the way of peace and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and they were gathered by this light, out of al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> crookedneſs, and perverſenſs, out of all lying, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> maliciouſneſs; for they was to put off anger, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſpeak the truth one to another; for the Lord<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> delight in them who walk in righteouſneſs be<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> him; ſaith Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>Let your yea be yea, your nay,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 5.37.</note> 
               <hi>nay,</hi> in all things, being faithful in wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> one towards another: faithfulneſs grows, ana<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſty grows, and uprightneſs grows, and ſo the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> come faithful, to bring forth fruit, To the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and glory of God: by this light was they ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> together, up to unity of ſpirit, <hi>they were a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized into one body,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 15.8. 1 Cor. 12.12, 13, 14. Eph. 4.4, 5, 6.</note> 
               <hi>by one Spirit, and they we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> made to drinke into one Spirit;</hi> they were come u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>to mount Sion, and unto the City of the living Ge<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> heavenly Jeruſalem, and to an innumerable c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> of Angels, and to the Spirits of juſt men made p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> the Church of the firſt born,</hi> Heb. 12.21, 22. The S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> did enjoy the ſubſtance of the ſecond cove<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> made manifeſt in them, which was Chriſt rea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> in them;<note place="margin">1 Cor. 2 7. Gal. 1.16.</note> the life of Chriſt was made manife<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> their mortal fleſh, and the glory of the Lord
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:34328:13"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>realed in them;<note place="margin">2 Cor. 4.10, 11. Rom. 8.1. 1 Joh. 2. 15, 16. Mat. 6.2.</note> they had the ſubſtance of what <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e firſt covenant did contain, which was outward, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Jew outwardly made manifeſt in them, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>y the light of God, revealing and manifeſting it to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>eir ſouls: after they came to the enjoyment of it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> cauſed them to deny the world, and they exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ed others to take heed of it, ſaying, <hi>Love not the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>orld, not the things of the world,</hi> for ſay they, <hi>If <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>y man love the world, the love of the Fther is not in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>im; no man can ſerve two maſters; they cannot <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>erve God and the world, for the love of the world <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> enmity with God;</hi> and by experience, from the enjoyment of this myſtery of godlineſs, made mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt in them, they ſaid, <hi>Eye hath not ſeen,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>ear hath not heard, neither hath it entred into the heart of man, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> conceive thoſe things that God hath laid up for thoſe that love him;</hi> The Saints did poſſeſs that which the world doth but now profeſs; they had the full enjoyment of thoſe things which the Scripture doth declare, and they did live the life of the righteous, and they were gathered, out of the world, and did walk up in obedience to the commands of God; therein was they known to differ from the world: for, ſaith Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>If you love me,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.6. 1 Joh. 5.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>keep my Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandments;</hi> now they did ſo, wherein ſay they, by <hi>this we know that we love God, becauſe we keep his Commandments, and his Commandments are not grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vious,</hi> but joyous, 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 2.3. It is the delight of thoſe that are borne againe, to do the will of God, none can but thoſe that are born anew, for every man by nature is a childre of wrath, <hi>and the naturall man, he knows not the things of God, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned,</hi> and again, <hi>no man knows the Son, but the Father, neither knoweth any man the Faher, but the Son, and he to whom the Son reveals him;</hi> all the wiſdom of the world cannot enter into the know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of this myſtery, to unfold it, it was revealed
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:34328:14"/>to the Saints, that had the enjoyment of it, wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the world hated, at every appearance of God in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> diſcovering himſelf to his people; the world is in e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity againſt it, <hi>marvel not if the world hate you:</hi> ſai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>it is not</hi> to be marvelled at; <hi>for</hi> ſaith he, <hi>hated me before it hated you,</hi> &amp; ſaith he, <hi>if ye were of i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> world,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Joh. 3.13. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oh. 15.17, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>3, 19, 20, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ak. 6.22, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. Pet. 4.13, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>at. 5.11, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>h. 17.18, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>, 20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>the world would love you, but becauſe I have cho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſen you out of the world, therefore doth the world ha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> you:</hi> and again ſaith he, <hi>Ye ſhall be hated of all men fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> my names ſake,</hi> but ſaith he, <hi>Bleſſed are you, when <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> revile you, and perſecute you, and ſay all manner <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> evill againſt you, falſly, for my names ſake, rejoyce a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> be exceeding glad, for great is your reward in He<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, for ſo perſecuted they the Prophets, that were before you;</hi> And where the Lord is appearing in his people now, great is the rage and madneſs of the world for whom God loves the world hates, nay the highe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> profeſſion perſecutes the Lord in his Saints, whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> he is made manifeſt in power; all profeſſion with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out poſſeſſion is hypocriſy and diſſimulation; Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the holy men of God were poſſeſſers, but the world now lives in words, deceiving themſelves, and di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembling both with God and man, and practiſing nothing but deceit: and the Prieſts are the grand enemies to Jeſus Chriſt, and the great deceivers of the people; they tell the people they are the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Jeſus Chriſt, and indeed they are Antichriſt, acting altogether againſt Chriſt; and they are the greateſt upholders of oppreſſion of any, which Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt came to throw down, the whole creati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is burdened by this ſtinking profeſſed Miniſtery; they act the ſame things that the Scribes and Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees did; they hold up thoſe things that Jeſus Chriſt came to throw down, and laid down his life for, and yet theſe deceivers that deceive the nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, ſay they are ſent of Chriſt, but they are found lyars; Jeſus Chriſt foretold of ſuch, that ſhould
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:34328:14"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ome, for ſaith he, <hi>there ſhall come falſe prophets in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eeps clothing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 7.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.16, 17, 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 19, 20, 21.</note> 
               <hi>but inwardly are ravening woolves,</hi> but ſaith he, <hi>By their fruits ye ſhall know them,</hi> Mat. 7. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey ſay, and do not. Is it not ſo with the falſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eachers in England? they ſay they are ſent of Chriſt, but he that ſaith he is in Chriſt,<note place="margin">1 Joh. 2.6.</note> ought to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>alk as he walked; Jeſus Chriſt was an example <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or all his to follow, and the Apoſtle who was a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>rue Miniſter of Chriſt, did exhort the people to <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ollow him,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 7.8, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, 10, 11, 12. &amp;c. Heb. 8.6, 7. &amp;c. Heb. 9.8, 9. Heb. 10.9.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſo far as he followed Christ;</hi> now Jeſus Chriſt came to take off oppreſſion from the people <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd to undo the heavy burdens that they groaned <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nder then, by the fair-ſayers, as thoſe hypocrites <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re now, that ſay and do not; Jeſus Chriſt came <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o take off that oppreſſion of Tythes, that was one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ing that he ſhed his blood for, but Antichriſt holds <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>up, which is contrary to Chriſt: Chriſt came to throw down the idols temple, and to throw down <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he outward worſhip, which the Jew outwardly had, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd to fulfill all that the law did contain outwardly, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hat he might place his law in their hearts, to be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>illed there: That he alone might teach them by his Spirit, without form,<note place="margin">Jer. 31.33.34. Heb. 8.10.11. Joh. 4.23.24.</note> to <hi>worſhip the Father in Spirit and in truth,</hi> Joh. 4. Now the falſe teachers in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and</hi> holds up the idols temple, and ſits in the ſeat of the Scribes and Phariſees, acting as in a ſtage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lay for money, all for filthy lucre, and proſeſſeth the Scripture to be their rule, when there is not a Scripture to warrant them for any thing they do. There is not a word in the Scripture for them to go to <hi>Cambridge</hi> or <hi>Oxford,</hi> to be ſo long there, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>earn a trade of deceit, to give a meaning to the Scripture, to gloſs them over, by their humane and ſerpentine wiſdome, to deceive people with their imaginations; but to the contrary, for the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, that <hi>every word of God is pure,</hi> and he that addeth thereto, or taketh therefrom, ſhall be
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:34328:15"/>reproved, and found a lyar, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30.5, 6. and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> gaine, ſee what the Lord ſaid to <hi>Moſes</hi> in <hi>Deut.</hi> 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Ye ſhall not adde unto the word which I command <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> but theſe goes contrary to the command of t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Lord, that goes to learn deceit, to add their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> mane wiſdom, to that which is truth in it ſelf; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> the Spirit of God could not underſtand its own d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration. And again, ſaith Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>I teſti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> that he that addes to the word of the prophecie, I w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> adde to him all the plagues that are written in the B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> Rev.</hi> ult. And again, it is ſaid, that <hi>no man knows <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Son, but the Father; neither knows any man the Fath<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> but the Son, and he to whom the Son reveals him,</hi> as i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>John.</hi> Then what uſe is all their brain-ſtudy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> It is all deceit, dung, and dirt: Away with it, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> with it; the Lord is coming to burn up all dece<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> and deceivers, and <hi>to ſcatter the proud in all their i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginations.</hi> Howl, ye proud Prieſts, for wo and miſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> is your portion: wo was the portion of the Scri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> and Phariſees, that laid heavie burdens upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> people, as theſe deceivers do, that deceive the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and bewitcheth them with thoſe things wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> God never commanded, telling the people that th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> are Ordinances of God. There is not a word in t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Scripture for ſprinkling Infants, and thoſe fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> Prieſts ſay that it is an Ordinance of Chriſt; a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> they can make Chriſtians (as they ſay) by ſprinkl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> them with a little water, and ſo entreth them i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Covenant; ſo making Chriſtians by their imagi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. Theſe are the falſe chriſts, and falſe proph<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> ſpoken of in Scripture. Now the Saints, they w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>baptized by one Sp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> m o one body,</hi> and they were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>of one heart and one minde.</hi> There is not a word <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Scripture for Tythe-mongers, and falſe teach<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> in <hi>England,</hi> to have the tenth of the yeers Incre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of all things for their brain-ſtudy, whereby they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the people, profeſſing themſelves to be the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſters
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:34328:15"/>of Chriſt, and act altogether againſt Chriſt, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ewing themſelves to be Antichriſts. What Scripture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ave they to take Tythe of wheat, rye, and barley? What Scripture have they for their rule, to take tithe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f oats, peaſe, and beans? What Scripture have they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>r their rule to take tythe of ſheep, the tenth lamb, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd the tenth fleece?<note place="margin">Eze. 34.2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 3.4. v. 16 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> But as it was amongſt the falſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eachers in Iſrael, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. ſo it is with the falſe tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hers in <hi>England</hi> now; they teach for the fleece, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed themſelves with the fat: but the Lord will feed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>uch with judgement.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ſe t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>eſt th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ipture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap> Saints <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>phold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> not of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>nding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>ng in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>mies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                     <desc>••••</desc>
                  </gap>gn in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>eer</note> What Scripture have they for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>heir rule, to take tythe of hemp, and flax, &amp; pigs? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd what Scripture have they for their rule, to take <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ythe-apples and plums, walnuts and cherries? what Scripture have they for their rule, to take money for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ggs, and to have tythe-geeſe? What Scripture have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hey for their rule, to take money for the reek paſſing <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>p the chimneys? What Scripture have they for their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ule, to take a peny for a garden every yeer? What Scripture have they for their rule, to take money for every foal that is foaled? What Scripture have they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>or their rule, to take money for every cow that hath a calf, and a peny for them that have none? What Scripture have they for their rule, to take a farthing of a ſhilling of ſervants for their wages? What Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture have they for their rule to Church women as they do, and take mony for it when they have done? What Scripture have they for their rule, to bury as they do, and take mony for it when they have done? did either Jeſus Chriſt, or his Apoſtles, that were the true Miniſter of the Goſpel ever do ſo? See if theſe be not the task-maſters of <hi>Egypt:</hi> there is ſcarce any thing, but theſe deceivers have an end in it, they are altogether for filthy lucre, contrary to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle to <hi>Timothy</hi> and <hi>Titus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 1, 2, 3. Tit. 1.7, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1 Pet 5.2, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> who were true Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Chriſt, <hi>Tit.</hi> 1.8, 9, 10. See who denies the Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptures, but thoſe that deny to walk according to them in life and converſation. For ſhame, down with
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:34328:16"/>oppreſſion: bluſh for ſhame, all ſuch deceivers, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> upholders of the deceits, and never profeſs love <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> God nor Chriſt,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſa. 33.14.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>5.</note> for your profeſſion is found to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> hypocriſie: and wo and miſery will be your porti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> except ye repent, &amp; give over deceiving the peop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Down with all deceivers,<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ude 11. v.</note> &amp; falſe worſhips; the gre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> day of the Lord is coming upon them all. What Sc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture have theſe for their rule, that have great ſu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> of money, ſo much a yeer, gifts and rewards, as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>laams</hi> prieſts had? What Scripture have they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> their rule, that have Augmentations? And what Scr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture have they for their rule, to go to law for tith<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> or for any thing elſe, that profeſs themſelves to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Miniſters of Chriſt? Neither Chriſt, nor any that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſent forth to preach the Goſpel, but all ſpoke again<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> it: ſaith Chriſt, <hi>Whoſoever ſhall ſue thee at the law, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> take away thy coat, let him have thy cloak alſo,</hi> Matth<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and the Apoſtle, who was a true Miniſter, ſpoke <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it: and they that ſay they are the Miniſters <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Chriſt, and act contrary to Chriſt, are Antichriſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> though they have never ſo fair a colour, they a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> but the coloured Beaſt, painted outſides; mar<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> them <hi>that ſay, and do not,</hi> thoſe are falſe Prophets<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
               <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. What Scripture have they any of them, t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> have <hi>the chiefeſt places in the Aſſemblies, and to b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> called of men maſters?</hi> The Scribes and Phariſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> had, which were enemies to Jeſus Chriſt; and thoſe that ſits in their ſeats are the ſame. What Scripture have they for their rule to go in long Robes, or in a colour differing from their brethren? The Scribes and Phariſees did ſo, which were enemies to Jeſus Chriſt. What Scripture have they for their rule to pray ſtanding in the Synagogues, before they preach as they call it, and after they have done? there is Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture to the contrary, where Jeſus Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Pray not ſtanding in the Synagogues.</hi> What Scripture have they for their rule, to be idle 6 days of 7, and then to go into the Idols temple, &amp; take a glaſs to ſpeak
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:34328:16"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; and none muſt ſpeak till they have done, nor then neither <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> there is to the contrary: In the true Church <hi>all may ſpeak, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t all may be edified;</hi> but it is plain that it is the falſe Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>of any thing be revealed to him that ſtood by,</hi> in the true Church <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>that had it revealed to him was to ſpeak, and the other was to hold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> peace,</hi> 2 Cor. 14. but it is not ſo now; he muſt be haled out the Apoſtles were by the Jews, and either beaten, or ſtoned, o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> impriſoned, and ſhut cloſe up, and not one to come at him, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>cept he give them money: all contrary to the Scripture, for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Apoſtle had more favour ſhewed of the Heathen, when he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> impriſoned, then the Saints of God have now, by thoſe that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>feſs themſelves to be Chriſtians, but it is plainly manifeſt that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y are enemies both to God and Chriſt. What Scripture <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ve they for their rule, profeſſing themſelves to be the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s of Jeſus Chriſt, to impriſon ſo many of the dear Saints <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſervants of the Lord, by a Law that was made to uphold <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Popiſh Clergie withal? See now whether theſe be not of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> generation of <hi>Cain,</hi> yea or no, and are of the devil, ſtanding <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ctual rebellion againſt Jeſus Chriſt, now that he is ariſing in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Saints: but the Lord will be avenged of all his enemies, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his adverſaries, and he alone will be honoured and reign in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Saints for ever and ever. The great day of the Lord is neer <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>and: Awake thou that ſleepeſt, and come to judgement: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> glittering ſword is drawn, it is four biſhed, and made fit for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſlaughter, to cut down to the ground all the enemies of the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>d: he <hi>will plead with all fleſh by his ſword and by fire, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>t ſhall be the ſlain of the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Oh <hi>England, England,</hi> repent, and turn to the Lord: Let the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e paſt of your lives be ſufficient, that you have wrought e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> and now turn from the evill of your ways; <hi>Let him that ſtole <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> no more:</hi> Let him that is proud forſake his pride and haugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſs; it is abomination to the Lord: Let <hi>Nabal</hi> forſake his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>lineſs, and the covetous man his covetouſneſs; Let the drun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d forſake his drunkenneſs; let the vain talkers forſake their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> talk, and put away their fooliſh jeſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ings, for God doth for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> it: Let the luſtful one take up the Croſs of Chriſt, that his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> may be ſacrificed up, that innocency may be head: let the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>s man forſake his envy, and let the inventor forſake his cun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:34328:17"/>inventions, and let the backbiter forſake his backb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> and the ſcoffing <hi>Iſhmael,</hi> his ſcoffing, and the ſcorner, le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> forſake his ſcornfulneſs, leſt his bands be made ſtrong: L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>wearer forſake his ſwearing; God doth forbid it; Let the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> forſake his lying, the falſe accuſer his falſe accuſations: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> you Prieſts and Lawyers, go and make reſtitution to who<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> have robbed. They that ſteal, they ſteal in the night; they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are drunk, are drunk in the night; but now the day is da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and the Day-ſtar is riſen, and the Sun begins to riſe; and h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> run forth in power, and you will be ſpyed out, where eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> are; all your old ſtore-houſes, your corrupt hearts m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſearched, the Lord is come, and is coming, let him come, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> will now be found guilty before the divine Magiſtrate, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> drawn his glittering ſword, it is ſharpe on both ſides, it hath <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> edges; wo, wo to you Prieſts and Lawyers, wo, wo to you p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> and luſtful ones, <hi>Iſa,</hi> 28.1, 2, 3. Let the oppreſſor forſake h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> preſſion; <hi>the earth is the Lords, and the fulneſs thereof:</hi> L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> bloodthirſty ones forſake their bloodthirſtineſs. The Magi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> bears not the ſword in vain, he will not ſuffer ſin to go u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iſhed: Awake, awake, and ſtand up to judgement, the L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> coming, the Lord is coming, in power and great glory, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> his power known upon all that act in unrighteouſneſs. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Prieſts and Lawyers, the Lord will plead with you all: ſta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap> awe of him, and tremble: you muſt all give up your acc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> and wo to the unjuſt, they muſt <hi>be turned into hell, and all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> that forget God:</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord, <hi>Will ye not fear me? <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ye not tremble at my preſence?</hi> Now the Trumpet begins to ſo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> Come out of your wickedneſs, and meet the Lord by tru<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, leſt your hearts be hardened, and your hands be <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſtrong, and ſo you be given up to a reprobate minde, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> into continual torment. Let the Adulterer forſake his Ad<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; for <hi>Adulterers and Whoremongers God will judge.</hi> No<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> new Law is found, and given forth of <hi>Sion;</hi> and as theſe are <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions, &amp; all unrighteouſneſs, and are covered over by a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſion, but all Covers muſt be ript, and ſtand before the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Magiſtrate, that hath and doth eſtabliſh this new <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> righteouſneſs, and he is a juſt Judge; look to it all, both grea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> ſmall, that act in unrighteouſneſs: Hear ye this, O heads <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> people; <hi>Let the time paſt ſuffice you, and now remove violen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> ſpoil, and execute judgement and juſtice, and take away your <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
